<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE jmax-doc SYSTEM 'jmax.dtd'>
<jmax-doc>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
	GridFlow Reference Manual: Architecture
	Copyright (c) 2001 by Mathieu Bouchard and Alexandre Castonguay
-->

<section name="Conventions of this Manual">
<prose>
	(This paragraph would be a duplicate of the one in reference.xml)
</prose>
</section>

<section name="Grid Protocol">
<prose>
	<p><i>This section is useful if you want to do more than just pictures
	with GridFlow.
	</i></p>
	<p>
	each element of a grid is an integer. the range of allowed integer values 
	is called <i>signed 32-bit</i> and is -2147483648 to 2147483647 (which 
	is -2<sup>31</sup> to 2<sup>31</sup>-1).
	</p>
	<p>
	a single-dimensional grid of 3 elements (a triplet) is called dim(3). a
	three-dimensional grid of 240 rows of 320 columns of triplets is called
	dim(240,320,3).
	</p>
	<p>
	There is a sequence in which elements of a Grid are stored and
	transmitted.  Dimension 0 is called "outer" or "first" and dimension N-1 is
	called  "inner" or "last". They are called so because if you select a
	position in the first dimension of a grid, the selected part is of the same
	shape minus the first dimension; so in dim(240,320,3) if you select
	row 51 (or whichever valid row number), you get a dim(320,3). if you select
	a subpart two more times you get to a single number.
	</p>
	<p>
	At each such level, elements are sent/stored in their numeric order, 
	and are numbered using natural numbers starting at 0. This ordering usually 
	does not matter, but sometimes it does. Most notably, <k>@import</k>, 
	<k>@export</k> and <k>@redim</k> care about it. 
	</p>
	<p>
	On the other hand, order of dimensions usually does matter; this is 
	what distinguishes rows from columns and channels, for example.
	Most objects care about the distinction.
	</p>
	<p>
	A grid with only 1 element in a given dimension is different from one
	lacking that dimension; it won't have the same meaning. You can use this
	property to your advantage sometimes.
	</p>
	<p>
	Zero-dimensional grids exist. They are called dim(). They can only contain
	a single number.
	</p>
</prose>
</section>

<section name="Picture Protocol">
<prose>
	<p><i>This section is useful if you want to know what a picture is
	in terms of a grid.
	</i></p>

	<p>A picture is a three-dimensional Grid: 
	<list start="0">
		<li>rows</li>
		<li>columns</li>
		<li>channels</li>
	</list>
	</p>
	<p>Channels for the RGB color model are:
	<list start="0">
		<li>red</li>
		<li>green</li>
		<li>blue</li>
	</list>
	</p>
	<p>
	Because Grids are made of 32-bit integers, a three-channel picture uses 
	96 bpp (bits per pixel), and have to be downscaled to 24 bpp (or 16 bpp) 
	for display. That huge amount of slack is there because when you create 
	your own effects you often have intermediate results that need to be of 
	higher precision than a normal picture. Especially, results of multiplications 
	are big and should not overflow before you divide them back to normal; 
	and similarly, you can have negative values all over, as long as you take 
	care of them before they get to the display.
	</p>
	<p>
	In the final conversion, high bits are just ignored. This means: black is
	0, maximum is 255, and values wrap like with <k>% 256</k>. If you want to
	clip them, you may use <k>"@ max 0"</k> and <k>"@ min 255"</k> objects. 
	</p>
</prose>
</section>

</jmax-doc>
