<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE jmax-doc SYSTEM 'jmax.dtd'>
<jmax-doc>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
        GridFlow Installation
        Copyright (c) 2001 by Mathieu Bouchard and Alexandre Castonguay
-->

<section name="Software (and Hardware) you Probably Need"><prose>
<p>Required Hardware (One of...):<list>
	<li>i386 : "old" IBM PC, or "new" IBM PC with old compiler</li>
	<li>i686 : "new" IBM PC with recent compiler</li>
	<li>ppc : "new" Macintosh (IS NOT SUPPORTED YET - HELP US)</li>
	<li>armv4l : Corel Netwinder (but jMax does not run on this)</li>
	<li>mips : Silicon Graphics, non-PC (only tested without jMax)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Required Software:<list>
	<li>Ruby 1.6 (language interpreter)</li>
	<li>GNU C Compiler (gcc)</li>
	<li>GNU Make (gmake)</li>
	<li>GNU Bash</li>
</list></p>
<p>Very Recommended:<list>
	<li>jMax 2.5</li>
	<li>jMax 3.0 support coming soon</li>
	<li>jMax 2.4 support removed</li>
	<li>X11 Display Server and MIT-Xlib (already in linux)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Optional:<list>
	<li>HeroineWarrior's libmpeg3.so</li>
	<li>HeroineWarrior's libquicktime.so</li>
	<li>Greg Ward's libmpeg.so ("Berkeley/MNI")</li>
	<li>a digitizer card with a Video4linux 1.x driver (videodev.h)</li>
	<li>Ruby 1.6 with package "xmlparser" (for editing documentation)</li>
</list></p>
<p>NOTE: 
for help on installing and compiling jMax, please see Christian Klippel's
extensive help file at <link to="http://www.mamalala.de"/>
as well as the jMax docs.</p>
<p>Also Useful:<list>
	<li>Pentium-compatible CPU (for profiling)</li>
	<li>CVS (for live update)</li>
</list></p>
<p>NOTE:
There are several different incompatible libmpeg's from different authors;
I found four of them, some numbered 2 and 3 as if they were version numbers
(but it seems they are not).
</p>

<p>NOTE: if one of your libraries are only available in .a format, you will not
be able to compile GridFlow. All libraries GridFlow uses must be in .so format.
</p>
</prose></section>

<section name="Installation process (for jMax 2.5)"><prose>
<list>
  <li>Install Ruby 1.6.6 or any version released in 2002 or later (the
latest from the 1.7 series work and are faster)  You will need the file
<k>libruby.so</k>, which is not always included. If you're using an
installer and you're missing the file, then look for another package of a
similar name that may contain extra files (eg: "ruby-dev"). If you're
installing from source code you have to configure with the
<k>--enable-shared</k> option. If you install into a system directory, you
have to recreate the library index using the <k>ldconfig</k> command too
(auto-installers normally do this for you).
  </li>

  <li>Download the latest version of GridFlow
      and download the images pack (gridflow-images-0.5.tar.gz).
      The download site is
	 <link to="http://www.artengine.ca/jmax/gridflow/download">artengine.ca</link>.
      Unpack Gridflow in /usr/local/jmax/packages (or the path of your choice),
      which will create a directory called 'gridflow';
      unpack the images pack into that directory, which will create
	 another one called 'images'.
  </li>

  <li>Find your jMax ARCH value. This is the one you use when installing
  jMax (or other jMax plugins other than GridFlow) manually. For K6,
  PentiumPro and such, on Linux, this is <k>i686-linux</k>. If you are
  trying to run it on a Macintosh, this would be <k>ppc-macosx</k> or
  <k>ppc-linux</k>.</li>

  <li>Run <k>./configure --jmax-arch <i>your-ARCH</i></k> from the
  <k>gridflow</k> directory. 
  note: if you didn't install GridFlow in the <k>jmax/packages</k>
  directory, then you have to add the option <k>--jmax-dist-dir
  <i>your-jmax-source-directory-goes-here</i></k>. Giving
  <k>/usr/lib/jmax</k> will not do because it wants <k>include</k> and
  <k>Makefiles</k> subdirectories, which do not get installed with
  jMax.</li>

  <li><k>./configure</k> will try to detect some optional components (libmpeg,
  pentium clock, etc); error messages may appear in case of a <k>no</k>.
  usually a <k>yes</k> will not show anything else. In the end, the files
  <k>config.make</k>,
  <k>c/src/Sources</k> and
  <k>c/src/config.h</k> will be generated.
  </li>

  <li>Stay in the same directory and do:
      <list>
        <li><k>make all</k></li>
        <li><k>make install</k></li>
      </list>
      but if the first one stops because of "Error" you shouldn't try the second
	 one.
  </li>

  <li>Load <k>~/.jmaxrc</k> (text). Go to the <k>when start</k> section.
  Add a line that says <k>package require gridflow</k>.
  Add this line that says <k>dataDirectory </k><i>gridflow-directory</i><k>/images</k>
  </li>

  <li>(Re)start jMax. </li>

</list>

  <p>Note: If there's a problem with libmpeg anywhere in the process,
  you can add the option --no-mpeg to the configurator.</p>

  <p>Note: If you want more speed, you can configure with the --fast
  switch, which turns off many error-detection mechanisms; if you want
  more speed, you could configure with --no-profiling too, but if you do
  that, you can no longer find out which of the objects consume the most
  time.</p>

</prose></section>

<section name="Installation process (without jMax)"><prose>
<list><li>
	If you don't have jMax installed it won't be detected. Installation
	will proceed normally except that the Ruby-for-jMax bridge won't be
	installed. Try running 'make test'. Look at 'tests/test.rb' for
	an example of how you may use GridFlow without jMax.
</li></list>
</prose></section>
</jmax-doc>
